Before we dive into the session material, let's talk a bit about storing or
persisting data in Android. First of all, why do we bother to persist things
at all? This is the era of the connected cloud. Why don't we always fetch from
there? It's really nice to not start the app and see, Loading, or, even worse,
like this, a blank screen. The faster people can use an app, the more it will be
used. Obviously, if one has to select Refresh, to get it to display anything,
that would be particularly bad. Another reason to persist our data,
is that using any radio is detrimental to the battery life of the device,
especially the cellular radio. Many users aren't on meter data plans or
may be roaming when they want to use your app. All those unnecessary data
fetches can add up. There are still lots of places that don't have a network
connection available. One of the prime advantages of having a mobile app is
being resistant to bad or non-existent network conditions. After all,
you never know where the user will want to use your app. As you might expect,
Android stores your persistent data in the file system.
These files can be stored in internal storage that is private to your app.
They can also be stored in shared or external storage. On older
Android devices this shared storage was actually on an external memory card.
Today, most Android devices only emulate this card so that there is
the shared external storage apps need available on the device. Some Android
devices have emulated shared storage and secondary external storage.
Android 4.4 Kit Kat added an API to allow developers to access this secondary
external storage. We're going to focus on internal storage in this class.
Check the instructor notes to learn more about Android storage locations.
As I mentioned before, Android persists data into the file system.
It does provide two functional layers on top of the file system in the form of
shared preferences and SQLite. The Shared Preferences class provides a general
framework that allows you to save and retrieve persistent key value pairs of
primitive data types, such as booleans, floats, ints, longs and
strings. Shared Preferences is used by the Android preference activity to store
our settings data such as the location. Why store things in a SQLite database?
After all, Android supports both RAW files and Shared Preferences. For
the same reason that it's inefficient to find things if you throw your
clothes in a pile on the floor. Storing things in an SQLite database helps
you organize and find data easily, thanks to the power of indexing in tables.
An SQLite database looks something like this fragment from our weather database.
Note that not all fields are represented. We can perform queries using
SQL against this database, such as the SELECT statement here, which returns
the weather on the specified date, similar to what we'll want to do for
the Detail view. We can use a slightly more complex query to return a range of
dates, which is similar to what we do on the main forecast ListView.